Register of the American Relief Administration Russian operational records
Hoover Institution Archives
- General Office, Russia File, 1921-1923
  Agreements, appeals, cables, correspondence, financial records, lists, memoranda, minutes of meetings, personnel records, printed matter, publicity material, and reports, arranged alphabetically by physical form.
  - Agreements (Box 531)
    - General - European Council, 1921 August 24 (Folder 1)
      Available on microfilm reel 632
    - ARA
      - Provisional Government of Russia (Folder 2)
      - Russian Political Conference (Folder 3)
      - Russian Volunteer Army (Folder 4)
      - Soviet Government (Folder 5)
  - Appeal by Maxim Gorky, 1921 July 13 (Folder 6)
  - Articles and clippings (Folder 7-8)
    Available on microfilm reel 633
  - Broadcast transcript from Moscow (Box 532, Folder 1)
    Available on microfilm reel 634
  - Cables
    - 1918 (Folder 2)
    - 1919 (Folder 3)
    - 1920 (Folder 4)
    - 1921 (Folder 5)
    - 1922 (Folder 6-7)
    - 1923 (Folder 8)
      Available on microfilm reel 635
  - Correspondence. Includes letters of Herbert Hoover to the President of the United States, 1922-1923
    - 1919 (Folder 9)
    - 1920 (Folder 10)
    - 1921 (Folder 11)
    - 1922 (Box 533, Folder 1-3)
    - 1923 (Folder 4)
      Available on microfilm reel 636
    - 1924 (Folder 5)
  - Financial records
    - General (Folder 6)
    - Audited accounts (Folder 7)
    - Balance sheets (Folder 8)
    - Bill (Folder 9)
    - Currency exchange reports (Box 534, Folder 1)
    - Index of prices in Moscow (Folder 2)
    - Receipts for Iudenich ruble (Folder 3)
    - Special treasury note (Folder 4)
  - Interview with Mr. Watt (Folder 5)
  - Letters from Petrograd (Folder 6)
  - Lists
    - Members of the Russian cabinet (Folder 7)
    - Universities and technical postgraduate schools in Russia (Folder 8)
  - Memoranda
    - General (Folder 9)
    - Meetings
      - General (Folder 10)
      - Hoover, Herbert (Folder 11)
  - Minutes of meetings
    - Executive Committee
      - 1921 August 25 (Folder 12)
      - 1922 July 30 (Folder 13)
    - Officers
      - 1922
        - March 13 (Folder 14)
        - May 16 (Folder 15)
        - October 20 (Folder 16)
        - October 23 (Folder 17)
        - November 20 (Folder 18)
        - November 27 (Folder 19)
      - 1923 January 26 (Folder 20)
    - Staff, 1922 December 29 (Folder 21)
    - Trustees
      - 1921 September 13 (Folder 22)
      - 1922 February 2 (Folder 23)
  - Personnel files (Folder 24-25)
    Available on microfilm reels 636 and 637
  - Personnel files (Box 535, Folder 1)
    Available on microfilm reel 637
  - Press excerpts (Folder 2)
  - Press releases (Folder 3)
  - Printed matter (Folder 4)
    Available on microfilm reel 638
  - Reports
    - General
      - Annual (Folder 5)
        Available on microfilm reel 639
      - Commerce (Folder 6)
      - Summaries (Folder 7)
    - Germany - Noah Meade trip to Berlin (Folder 8)
    - Nansen High Commissariat (Folder 9)
    - Russia (Folder 10)
  - Russian Unit records (Folder 11)
  - Russian Unit records (Box 536, Folder 1-3)
    Available on microfilm reels 639 and 640
  - Shipping records (Folder 4)
    Available on microfilm reel 640
  - Speeches (Folder 5)
  - Subject file (Box 537)
    - General (Folder 1)
    - All Russian Union of Zemstvos for Relief of the Sick and Wounded Soldiers (Folder 2)
    - American prisoners in Russia (Folder 3)
    - Ashland Textile Co. (Folder 4)
    - Central Supply Committee of the Russian Armies (Folder 5)
    - Commodities shipped to Russia (Folder 6)
      Available on microfilm reel 641
    - Food situation (Folder 7)
    - Gifts from the American people (Folder 8)
    - Institute of Politics (Folder 9)
    - International Red Cross (Folder 10)
    - Maize (Folder 11)
    - Manganese mines (Folder 12)
    - Medical supplies (Folder 13)
    - North-Western Army
      - General (Folder 14)
      - Agreement between the Government of Estonia and General Iudenich (Folder 15)
      - Correspondence (Folder 16)
      - Incomplete list of major events in Russian North-Western Territory (Folder 17)
      - Memoranda (Folder 18)
      - Military orders (Folder 19)
      - Military reports (Folder 20)
      - Protocols of the Liquidation Commission (North-Western Army) (Folder 21)
    - Prisoners of war (Folder 22)
    - Russian Academy of Science (Folder 23)
    - Russian committees in France (Folder 24)
    - Russian Government contribution (Folder 25)
    - Russian industry and industrial policy (Folder 26)
    - Russian negotiations (Folder 27)
    - Russian recognition (Folder 28)
    - Russian Refugee Relief Society in America (Folder 29)
    - Russian refugees
      - General (Folder 30)
      - Austria (Folder 31)
      - China (Folder 32)
      - Czechoslovakia (Folder 33)
      - Miscellaneous (Folder 34)
    - Russian Scientific Aid Society (Folder 35)
    - Russian Unit. Historical Division (Folder 36)
    - Russian Zemstvos and Towns Relief Committee (Folder 37)
    - Sales of products (Folder 38)
    - Sales Promotion Committee (Folder 39)
    - Siberia (Folder 40)
    - Supplies shipped into Russia up to, 1922 November 10 (Folder 41)
    - Ukraine (Folder 42)
    - Ukrainian National Committee (Folder 43)
    - Union of Russian Emigrant Students' Organizations (Folder 44)
    - Miscellany. Typescript, "The Psychology of the Russian Peasant" (Folder 45)
- European Children's Fund, Russia File, 1919-1928
  Available on microfilm reels 641-650
  Agreements, articles, bulletins, cables, correspondence, clippings, financial records, memoranda, news summaries, personnel records, press releases, printed matter, reports, and statistics, arranged alphabetically by physical form.
  - Agreements, Includes some correspondence, 1921-1923. (Box 538, Folder 1)
  - Articles, 1920-1922 (Folder 2)
  - Bulletins, 1922 (Folder 3)
  - Cables
    - 1919 (Folder 4)
    - 1920 (Folder 5)
    - 1921 (Folder 6)
    - 1922 (Folder 7)
      Available on microfilm reel 642
    - 1923 (Folder 8)
  - Circular letters (Box 539)
    - 1921 (Folder 1)
    - 1922
      - January-June (Folder 2)
      - July-December (Folder 3)
    - 1923 (Folder 4)
  - Correspondence
    - 1919 (Folder 5)
    - 1920 (Folder 6)
    - 1921 (Folder 7)
    - 1922
      - January-February (Folder 8)
        Available on microfilm reel 643
      - March-December (Folder 9)
    - 1923 (Folder 10)
    - 1924-1927 (Folder 11)
  - Financial records. Accounts, cables, correspondence, memoranda, and reports (Box 540)
    - 1921-1922 (Folder 1)
    - 1923 (Folder 2)
      Available on microfilm reel 644
  - Historical file, Article, correspondence, and report, 1923-1929. (Folder 3)
  - Memoranda, 1921-1928 (Folder 4)
  - News summaries
    - 1922 (Folder 5)
    - 1923 (Folder 6)
  - Personnel file, Cables, certificate, chart, correspondence, and memoranda, 1920-1924. (Folder 7)
  - Plans, 1921 (Box 541, Folder 1)
  - Publicity file, Correspondence, memorandum, and press releases, 1922. (Folder 2)
  - Reports, 1919-1922 (Folder 3)
    Available on microfilm reel 645
  - Shipping records, Cables and correspondence, 1920-1922. (Folder 4)
  - Statistics, Tables, 1920-1922. (Folder 5)
  - Subject file, Articles, cables, correspondence, memoranda, printed matter, receipts, and reports, 1919-1928.
    - Accidents (Folder 6)
    - Adult feeding (Folder 7)
    - American Central Committee for Russian Relief, Inc. (Folder 8)
    - American Committee for Relief of Russian Children (Folder 9)
    - American Friends Service Committee
      - 1921
        - January-June (Folder 10)
        - July-December (Box 542, Folder 1)
      - 1922-1923 (Folder 2)
    - American Jewish Joint Distribution Committee (Folder 3)
    - American Red Cross (Folder 4)
    - Bags (Folder 5)
    - Baum, Harlowe, and Co. (Folder 6)
    - Beeuwkes, Henry (Folder 7)
    - Blankets (Folder 8)
    - Childs, J. Rives (Folder 9)
      Available on microfilm reel 646
    - Clothing and shoes (Folder 10)
    - Codes (Box 543, Folder 1)
    - Colton, E. T. (Folder 2)
    - Counterfeiting (Folder 3)
    - Danchakoff, Vera (Folder 4)
    - Darrach, William (Folder 5)
    - Doctors (Folder 6)
    - Espionage allegations (Folder 7)
      Available on microfilm reel 647
    - Feldman, Anna (Folder 8)
    - Finley, John H. (Folder 9)
    - Foltz family (Folder 10)
    - Food remittances (Box 544, Folder 11-12)
      Available on microfilm reel 647 or 648
    - Gibbs, Philip, Sir (Folder 1)
    - Golder, Frank (Folder 2)
    - Goodrich, J. P. (Folder 3)
    - Government contributions (Folder 4)
    - Grain
      - 1921 (Folder 5)
      - 1922
        - January (Folder 6)
          Available on microfilm reel 648
        - February (Folder 7)
        - March-December (Folder 8)
      - 1923 (Folder 9)
    - Haskell, William, Mr. and Mrs.
      - 1919-1920 (Folder 10)
      - 1921-1923 (Folder 11)
    - Hibben, Paxton (Box 545, Folder 1)
    - Inspections (Folder 2)
    - Intelligentsia (Folder 3)
    - International Committee of the Red Cross (Folder 4)
    - Iudenich, Nikolai. Includes material concerning the Russian Northwestern Government (Folder 5)
      Available on microfilm reel 649
    - Larsen, Lauritz (Folder 6)
    - Latvian Red Cross (Folder 7)
    - Laura Spelman Rockefeller Memorial (Folder 8)
    - Mail and courier service (Folder 9)
    - Medical supplies, 1922
      - January-June (Folder 10)
      - July-December (Folder 11)
    - Mennonite Central Committee (Box 546)
      - 1921 (Folder 1)
      - 1922 (Folder 2)
      - 1923 (Folder 3)
    - Motion pictures (Folder 4)
    - Motor vehicles (Folder 5)
      Available on microfilm reel 650
    - Nansen, Fridtjof (Folder 6)
    - National Civic Federation (Folder 7)
    - Oats (Folder 8)
    - Refugees
      - General (Folder 9)
      - Balkans (Folder 10)
      - Germany (Folder 11)
      - Switzerland (Folder 12)
    - Refunds (Box 547, Folder 1)
    - Russian Red Cross (Folder 2)
    - Russian Student Fund, Inc. (Folder 3)
    - Save the Children Fund (Folder 4)
    - Taylor, Alonzo (Folder 5)
- Miscellany, 1917-1937
  Available on microfilm reels 651-664
  Documents and records collected from various A.R.A. offices and missions relating to relief efforts in Russia, arranged alphabetically by physical form.
  - Histories (Box 548)
    - Fisher, Harold H.
      - "The Famine in Soviet Russia, ", 1919-1923
        - General. Includes a book jacket and some correspondence (Folder 1)
          Available on microfilm reel 651
        - Agreements with publishers and loyalty contracts (Folder 2)
        - Correspondence
          - General. Includes personal correspondence (Folder 3-4)
          - American Railway Express (Folder 5)
          - CRB Educational Foundation, Inc. Includes memoranda about the introduction of the book (Folder 6)
          - Macmillan Company (Folder 7)
        - Draft of typewritten manuscript. Includes copies of rejected or rewritten chapters (Folder 8)
        - Index to text. Includes correspondence concerning proof of the index (Folder 9)
        - Letters of acknowledgment of gifts from institutions such as universities libraries, historical societies, archives, public libraries, non-profit organizations, and other relief organizations. Also includes letters from institutions from abroad (Folder 10-11)
          Available on microfilm reel 652
        - Letters of acknowledgment of gifts from institution such as universities libraries, historical societies, archives, public libraries, non-profit organizations, and other relief organizations. Also includes letters from institutions from abroad (Box 549, Folder 1)
        - Lists of names for distribution of book
          - General
            - General. Includes lists of names from Frank A. Golder (Folder 2)
            - Certificate copies (Folder 3)
            - Special distribution list of George Barr Baker (Folder 4)
          - Libraries (Folder 5)
        - Maps and charts to use as supporting materials for the book. Includes some correspondence and an annual report of, 1922 (Folder 6)
        - Names of personnel and members of the Russian Unit, 1921-1923 (Folder 7)
        - Proposed outlines of chapters and parts (Folder 8)
          Available on microfilm reel 653
        - Reviews
          - General (Folder 9)
          - Clippings of press reviews. Includes some correspondence (Folder 10)
          - Copy of review written by H. Alexander Smith. Includes some correspondence and notes (Folder 11)
          - Requests for reviews of the manuscript (Folder 12)
        - Samples of book title for proof (Folder 13)
  - Subject file (Box 550)
    - General
      - New Economic Policy and productions of Russian industries (Folder 1)
      - Russian Agricultural Scientific Committee - Cereal investigation (Borodin, D. N.) (Folder 2)
      - Press releases (in Russian) (Folder 3)
      - Propaganda. Includes newspaper clippings, records of Senate hearings, issues of Congressional Record, magazine articles, correspondence, reports, and other printed materials (Folder 4-6)
        Available on microfilm reel 654
      - Propaganda. Includes newspaper clippings, records of Senate hearings, issues of Congressional Records, magazine articles, correspondence, reports, and other printed materials (Box 551, Folder 1-3)
        Available on microfilm reels 654 and 655
    - Russian famine relief (Box 552)
      - General
        - General
          - General. Includes one document relating to land reform in, 1917-1918 (Folder 1)
            Available on microfilm reel 655
          - Cables
            - Germany (East) (Folder 2)
            - Price, Frank J. (Folder 3)
            - Prices (Folder 4)
            - Ports (Folder 5)
            - Postcards (appeals) (Folder 6)
            - Purchases (Folder 7)
            - Rye (Folder 8)
            - United States Department of State (Folder 9)
            - Ukraine (Folder 10)
            - Walker, H. C. (Folder 11)
            - Warsaw (Folder 12)
            - YMCA (Folder 13)
            - YWCA (Folder 14)
          - Correspondence
            - General. Includes confidential letters (Folder 15-16)
            - London Office (from Riga and Moscow)
              - 1920 January 31 -September 25 (Folder 17)
              - 1921 August 2 -November 30 (Folder 18)
                Available on microfilm reel 656
              - 1921 December 1-1922 January 3 (Folder 19)
              - 1922
                - January 3 -February 7 (Folder 20)
                - February 8 -March 4 (Folder 21)
            - New York Office and Washington Office (Box 553)
              - 1920 January 2 -September 27 (Folder 1)
              - 1921
                - July 30 -November 29 (Folder 2)
                - 31, December 8- (Folder 3)
                Available on microfilm reel 657
              - 1922
                - January 3 -February 7 (Folder 4)
                - February 8 -March 3 (Folder 5)
              - 1923-1925 (Folder 6)
            - Prague Office (Folder 7)
          - Minutes of meetings and memoranda (Box 554)
            - General (Folder 1)
              Available on microfilm reel 658
            - Supply Division. Memorandum no. 14 (Folder 2)
          - Personnel records (Folder 3)
          - Printed matter. Includes The Red Cross Bulletin published by the American Red Cross Commission to Western Russia and the Baltic States, Volume 1, 1920 (Folder 4)
          - Reports
            - General (Folder 5)
            - "American Medical and Sanitary Relief in the Russian Famine, " by Henry Beeuwkes, 1921-1923 (Folder 6)
          - Shipping schedule in chronological order, 1922 July 1 -December 1 (Folder 7)
          - Statistics - Monthly medical and sanitary statistics of the Medical Division
            - 1921 December-1922 January (Folder 8)
            - 1922
              - March (Folder 9)
              - April (Folder 10)
              - May (Folder 11)
              - June (Folder 12)
              - July (Folder 13)
                Available on microfilm reel 659
        - Amalgamated Clothing Workers of America (Box 555, Folder 1)
        - American Committee for Relief of Russian Children (Folder 2)
        - American Federated Russian Famine Relief Committee (Folder 3)
        - American Jewish Joint Distribution Committee (Folder 4)
        - American Medical Aid for Russia (Folder 5)
        - American Relief for Russian Women and Children (Folder 6)
        - Federal Council of the Churches of Christ in America
          - General (Folder 7)
          - Credits and Accounting Department records (Folder 8)
        - National Catholic Welfare Council
          - General, 1921-1924 (Folder 9)
          - Credits and Accounting Department records (Folder 10)
        - North American Archdiocese of the Russian Orthodox Greek Catholic Church (Folder 11)
        - Rockefeller Foundation
          - Appropriation (Folder 12)
            Available on microfilm reel 660
          - Distribution (Box 556, Folder 1)
          - Unexpended balance (Folder 2)
        - South Russia Relief Society (Folder 3)
        - United Russian Relief Society (Folder 4)
      - Baptist relief
        - 1921-1922 (Folder 5)
        - 1923-1924 (Folder 6)
      - Jewish relief
        - All Russian Jewish Public Committee for Relief of Pogrom and War Sufferers (Folder 7)
        - American Jewish Relief Committee for Sufferers from the War (Folder 8)
          Available on microfilm reel 661
        - Hebrew Sheltering and Immigrant Aid Society of America (Folder 9)
        - Jewish National Relief Committee (Box 557, Folder 1)
        - Jewish People's Relief Committee (Folder 2)
        - National Federation of Ukrainian Jews of America (Folder 3)
      - Lutheran relief
        - General
          - 1921-1922 (Folder 4)
          - 1923-1924 (Folder 5)
            Available on microfilm reel 662
        - Accounting Department records (Folder 6)
      - Mennonite relief
        - General
          - 1921-1922 (Folder 7)
          - 1923 (Box 558, Folder 1)
        - Accounting Department records (Folder 2)
      - Methodist relief (Folder 3)
      - Student feeding
        - General (Folder 4)
        - Reports (Folder 5)
        - Student Friendship Fund (Folder 6)
    - Russian Unit
      - Bills of lading for transportation and shipments (Folder 7)
      - Comite Carpatho-Russe (Carpatho-Russian Committee). Petition for aids for Carpatho-Russians (Folder 8)
      - Copies of agreements of the Russian operation. Includes some original letters and memoranda (Folder 9)
      - Correspondence. Letters acknowledging receipts of bulletins, reports, and other miscellaneous correspondence (Folder 10)
      - Financial records. Includes shipping lists, commodity statistics, packing lists for food and clothing remittances, personnel information, and other miscellaneous correspondence relating to the compilation of ARA histories (Folder 11)
        Available on microfilm reel 663
      - Letters from Edward M. Flesh to Christian A. Herter of the Department of Commerce (Box 559, Folder 1)
      - Press releases. Includes one newspaper article (Folder 2)
      - Receipts from Soviet government for inventory auditing on properties such as warehouses, personnel houses, and equipment which were purchased with Soviet funds and used by ARA
        - General. Includes correspondence regarding government audit (Folder 3)
        - Crimea (Folder 4)
        - Ekaterinoslav (Folder 5)
        - Elizabethgrad (Folder 6)
        - Gomel (Folder 7)
        - Kazan (Folder 8)
        - Kharkov (Folder 9)
        - Kiev (Folder 10)
        - Minsk (Folder 11)
        - Moscow (Folder 12)
          Available on microfilm reel 664
        - Odessa (Folder 13)
        - Orenburg (Folder 14)
        - Petrograd (Folder 15)
        - Rostov-Tzaritzen (Folder 16)
        - Samara (Folder 17)
        - Saratov (Folder 18)
        - Simbirsk (Folder 19)
        - Vitebsk (Folder 20)
        - Ufa (Folder 21)
      - Statements showing metric tonnage of commodities received and discharged at Russian ports together with quantity evacuated to interior and quantity held in storage, 1922 March 25 (Folder 22)
- Incremental Materials
  - Framed reproductions of letters written by Herbert Hoover in English and Russian (Box 560)
  - American Relief Administration cloth bag (Box 561)
  - Not yet described (Box 562)